When I was only three or four,
عندما كان عمري ثلاث أو أربع سنوات فقط،
I fell in love with poetry,
أحببت الشِّعر،
with the rhythms and the music of language;
أحببت إيقاعات وموسيقى اللغة؛
with the power of metaphor and of imagery,
أحببت قوة المجاز والتشبيه،
poetry being the essence of communication --
فالشعر يُعتبر جوهر التواصل --
the discipline, the distillation.
ويمثل التهذيب والخلاصة.
And all these years later, the poems I'll read today
وبعد كل هذه السنين، القصائد التي سوف ألقيها عليكم اليوم
are from my just-finished seventh book of poetry.
هي من ديواني الشعري السابع الذي انتهيت من كتابته مؤخرًا.
Well, five years ago, I was diagnosed with Parkinson's disease.
حسنا، قبل خمس سنوات، تم تشخيص إصابتي بمرض باركنسون.
Though there's no cure yet,
مع أنه لم يكتشف له علاج بعد،
advances in treatment are really impressive.
إلا أن التطور في توفير العلاج مثير للإعجاب.
But you can imagine that I was appalled to learn
لكن لكم أن تتخيلوا كم كان من المرعب بالنسبة لي معرفة
that women are largely left out of research trials,
أن النساء في الغالب مستبعدات من الأبحاث التجريبية،
despite gender-specific medical findings having demonstrated
على الرغم من أن الإكتشافات الطبية حسب الجنس أظهرت
that we are not actually just small men --
أننا لسنا فقط رجالًا صغارًا --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
who happen to have different reproductive systems.
قدر لهم أن يحصلوا على أجهزة تناسلية مختلفة،
Gender-specific medicine is good for men, too.
الطب حسب الجنس جيد للرجال أيضًا.
But you bring to a crisis the person you already are,
ولكنك في أزمة من تكون حاليا،
including the, yes, momentum that you've learned to invoke
بما في ذلك، نعم، الزخم الذي تعلمت الإعتماد عليه
through passionate caring and through action,
من خلال الرعاية الجيدة والعمل،
both of which require but also create energy.
كلاهما يتطلب بل ويولد الطاقة.
So as an activist, I began working with the Parkinson's Disease Foundation --
لذلك وكناشطة، بدأت العمل مع مؤسسة مرض باركنسون
that's pdf.org --
وموقعها الإلكتروني هو pdf.org
to create a major initiative to put women on the Parkinson's disease map.
من أجل خلق مبادرة كبرى بغرض وضع النساء على خارطة مرض باركنسون.
And as a poet, I began working with this subject matter,
وكشاعرة، بدأت العمل على هذا الأمر،
finding it tragic, hilarious, sometimes even joyful.
حيث اكتشفت أنه شيئ مأساوي، مثير للضحك وأحيانا حتى ممتع.
I do not feel diminished by Parkinson's;
لا أشعر بأنني ضعيفة كنتيجة لمرض باركنسون
I feel distilled by it,
أشعر بأنه ينقيني،
and I actually very much like the woman I'm distilling into.
وفي الواقع أحب جدًا ما أنا عليه الآن.
"No Signs of Struggle"
"استسلام"
Growing small requires enormity of will:
النمو في الصغر يتطلب إرادة ضخمة:
just sitting still in the doctor's waiting room
مثل أن تجلس في غرفة الإنتظار عند الطبيب
watching the future shuffle in and out,
مراقبًا المستقبل يختلط في الداخل والخارج،
watching it stoop; stare at you
تراقبه وهو ينحني، يحدق فيك
while you try not to look.
بينما تحاول أنت الإشاحة بنظرك.
Rare is an exchange:
النادر هو ما يبقى
a smile of brief, wry recognition.
ابتسامة عابرة، اعتراف ساخر.
You are the new kid on the block.
أنت الطفل الجديد في الحي.
Everyone here was you once.
كل المتواجدين هنا كانوا مثلك من قبل.
You are still learning that growing small requires a largeness of spirit
مازلت تتعلم أن النمو في الصغر يتطلب سعة في الروح
you can't fit into yet:
لا يسعك تقمصها بعد:
acceptance of irritating help from those who love you;
قبول المساعدة على مضض من أشخاص يحبونك
giving way and over, but not up.
يفسح المجال وأكثر، ولكن لا تَصَلْ.
You've swallowed hard the contents of the "Drink Me" bottle,
لقد تجرعت ما تحويه زجاجة "اشربني"،
and felt yourself shrink.
وشعرت بنفسك تنكمش.
Now, familiar furniture looms,
الآن، أثاث مألوف يلوح في الأفق،
floors tilt, and doorknobs yield only when wrestled round with both hands.
إمالة طوابق، ومقابض أبواب تذعن فقط عند صرعها بكلتا اليدين.
It demands colossal patience, all this growing small:
يتطلب صبرا هائلا، كل هذا يتنامى في الصغر:
your diminished sleep at night,
قِلَّتُ نومك ليلا،
your handwriting, your voice, your height.
خط يدك، صوتك، طولك.
You are more the incredible shrinking woman
أنت المرأة المتقلصة الرائعة
than the Buddhist mystic, serene, making do with less.
أكثر من بوذي متصوف، هادئ، يفعل بأقل جهد.
Less is not always more.
القليل ليس متوفرًا دائمًا.
Yet in this emptying space, space glimmers,
في هذا الفضاء الفارغ، يومض الفضاء،
becoming visible.
يصبح مَرِْئيًا.
Here is a place behind the eyes of those accustomed
كانت هنا عينان
by what some would call diminishment.
سيدعوها البعض التقليل.
It is a place of merciless poetry,
حيث مكان الشعر الذي لا يرحم،
a gift of presence previously ignored,
هدية حضور تم تجاهله،
drowned in the daily clutter.
غارقة في فوضى يومية.
Here every gesture needs intention,
كل ايماءة تدفعها نية،
is alive with consciousness.
حية الضمير.
Nothing is automatic.
لا شيء تلقائي.
You can spot it in the provocation of a button,
تلحظه في ضغطة زر،
an arm poking at a sleeve,
ذراع مدسوسة في الأكمام،
a balancing act at a night-time curb while negotiating the dark.
تحقيق التوازن في ليل مكبوح الجماح حين مفاوضة الليل.
Feats of such modest valor,
مآثر بسالة متواضعة،
who would suspect them to be exercises in an intimate, fierce discipline,
من لِيَشَّكَ فيهم حتى يهذبهم بطريقة حميمة صارمة،
a metaphysics of being relentlessly aware?
ميتافيزيقية الإدراك بلا هوادة؟
Such understated power here,
هكذا سلطة ضعيفة،
in these tottering dancers who exert stupendous effort
مع هؤلاء الراقصين المترنحين الذين يبذلون جهدًا هائلًا
on tasks most view as insignificant.
في واجبات لا تثير الإهتمام.
Such quiet beauty here, in these,
مثل هذا الجمال الهادئ،
my soft-voiced, stiff-limbed people;
صوتي الهادئ، شعب صلب ذات الأطراف
such resolve masked by each placid face.
هكذا أقنعة على كل وجه وديع.
There is immensity required in growing small,
النمو في الصغر يتطلب اتساعًا
so bent on such unbending grace.
نعمة لا تحصى.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
This one is called "On Donating My Brain to Science."
هذه القصيدة تدعى "تبرعًا بذهني للعلوم."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Not a problem.
لا مشكلة.
Skip over all the pages reassuring religious people.
تخطى كل الصفحات مطمئنًا المتدينين.
Already a universal donor: kidneys, corneas, liver, lungs,
إذا ما كنت متبرعًا عالميًا: الكليتين، والقرنيتين، والكبد، والرئتين،
tissue, heart, veins, whatever.
والأنسجة، والقلب، والأعصاب، وأيّا كان.
Odd that the modest brain never imagined its unique value in research,
عقل لا يقدر قيمته للبحوث،
maybe saving someone else from what it is they're not quite sure I have.
ربما أن تنقذ شخصا آخر من ما لا يعلمون أني أملكه.
Flattering, that.
ذاك مجرد إغراء.
So fill in the forms,
لذا، إتخذ مكانك،
drill through the answers,
تعمق في الإجابات،
trill out a blithe spirit.
زغرودة من روح مبتهجة.
And slice me, dice me, spread me on your slides.
ومن ثم شرِّحني، العبني كزهر نرد، واطرحني على مزلاقك.
Find what I'm trying to tell you.
اكتشف مكنونات صدري.
Earn me, learn me, scan me, squint through your lens.
اكسبني، علمني، افحصني، ذاك الحول البادي في عينيك.
Uncover what I'd hint at if I could.
ازح الستار عن ما أخفيته طوعًا.
Be my guest, do your best, harvest me, track the clues.
كن ضيفي، افعل ما شئت، اقتطفني، تقفى الحقائق.
This was a good brain while alive.
كان هذا دماغا جيدًا.
This was a brain that paid its dues.
كان هذا دماغا ملتزمًا.
So slice me, dice me, smear me on your slides,
شرحني، العب بي كحجر نرد، ادهني على شرائحك،
stain me, explain me, drain me like a cup.
الطخني، اشرحني، فرِّغْني كباقي كوب.
Share me, hear me:
تشاركني، اسمعني:
I want to be used
أود أن تتم الإستفادة مني
up.
أود أن تتم الإستفادة مني.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Applause ends)
(انتهاء التصفيق)
And this one's called "The Ghost Light."
القصيدة التالية تدعى "ضوء الروح."
Lit from within is the sole secure way
أن تضيء بنورك هو أضمن طريق
to traverse dark matter.
لتعبر أي أمر شائك.
Some life forms -- certain mushrooms, snails, jellyfish, worms --
بعض أشكال الحياة وبعض الفطر والقواقع وقنديل البحر والديدان -
glow bioluminescent,
تلألئ بيولوجي،
and people as well;
وكذلك الناس:
we emit infra-red light from our most lucent selves.
ذواتنا المتألقة تبعث أشعة تحت حمراء.
Our tragedy is we can't see it.
مأساتنا أنَّنا لا نرى ذلك.
We see by reflecting.
نحن نرى عن طريق الإنعكاس.
We need biofluorescence to show our true colors.
نحن بحاجة إلى اشعاع بيولوجي لنظهر دواخلنا الحقيقية.
External illumination can distort, though.
العالم الخارجي قد يشوهنا.
When gravity bends light,
عندما تفقد الجاذبية قوتها ببطء،
huge galaxy clusters can act as telescopes,
المجرات الضخمة يمكن أن تكون بمثابة تلسكوبات،
elongating background images of star systems to faint arcs --
خلفية النجوم
a lensing effect
تأثير التصوير
like viewing distant street lamps through a glass of wine.
مثل أن ترى أضواء المدينة البعيدة من خلال كأس نبيذ.
A glass of wine or two now makes me weave
كأس نبيذ أو اثنان يجعلني أتمايل
as if acting the drunkard's part;
وكأن ألعب دور السكير:
as if, besotted with unrequited love
أشبه بالمأخوذ بحب بلا مقابل
for the dynamic Turner canvasses spied out by the Hubble,
لقماش تورنر الحيوي تجسس عليه هابل،
I could lurch down a city street set
بمقدوري أن أتمايل في شوارع المدينة
without provoking every pedestrian walk-on stare.
دون إثارة المشاة المحدِّقين.
Stare as long as you need to.
حدِّق كما تشاء.
If you think about it, walking, even standing, is illogical --
إن كنت تفكر في الأمر، المشي وحتى الوقوف شيئ غير منطقي
such tiny things, feet! --
مثل هكذا أشياء صغيرة، قدم!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
especially when one's body is not al dente anymore.
بخاصة حينما لا يستوي الجسد بعد الآن.
Besides, creature of extremes and excess,
إلى جانب ذلك، مخلوق من الإفراط والزيادة،
I've always thought Apollo beautiful but boring,
لطالما فكرت أن أبولو جميل ولكن ممل،
and a bit of a dumb blonde.
وقليلًا من شقراء غبية.
Dionysians don't do balance.
ديونيسيس لا يحدث التوازن.
Balance, in other words, has never been my strong point.
لم يحدث أن كان التوازن نقطة قوتي.
But I digress.
ولكن سأستطرد.
More and more these days,
أكثر وأكثر هذه الأيام،
digression seems the most direct route through
يبدو أن الإستطراد هو أكثر طريق مباشر
from where I've lost or found myself
من حيث فقدت أو وجدت نفسي
out of place, mind, turn, time.
خارج إطار المكان والعقل والجولة والوقت.
Place your foot just so, mind how you turn:
ضع أقدامك فقط، انتبه لإستدارتك:
too swift a swivel can bring you down.
دوران سريع جدًا قد يطيح بك أرضًا.
Take your time ushering the audience out,
خذ وقتك وأعلن للجمهور،
saying goodbye to the actors.
قل وداعا للممثلين.
The ghost light
ضوء الروح
is what they call the single bulb
هو ما يسمونه المصباح الوحيد
hanging above the bare stage in an empty theater.
معلقا فوق خشبة عارية في مسرح خالي.
In the empty theater of such a night,
في مسرح فارغ في هكذا ليلة،
waking to meet no external radiance,
حتى لا أقابل أي توهج خارجي،
this is the final struggle left to win,
هذا آخر ما تبقي لي حتى أنتصر،
this the sole beacon to beckon the darkness in
هذا هو المشعل الوحيد لإضاءة الظلام
and let the rest begin,
والبقية تأتي،
this the lens through which at last to see both Self and Other
هي العدسة التي من خلالها أرى نفسي والأشعة
arrayed with the bright stain of original sin:
الأخرى على صورتها الحقيقية:
lit from within.
أضئ بنورك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And this is the last one.
وهذه آخر واحدة.
"This Dark Hour"
"هذه الساعة المظلمة."
Late summer, 4 A.M.
الصيف الماضي، الرابعة صباحًا
The rain slows to a stop,
المطر يتباطئ حتى التوقف،
dripping still from the broad leaves
يقطر من أوراق الشجر الكبيرة
of blue hostas unseen in the garden's dark.
زرقاء لا ترى في ظلام الحديقة.
Barefoot, careful on the slick slate slabs,
أقدام حافية، بحذر على ألواح الأردواز الزلقة،
I need no light, I know the way,
لست بحاجة إلى ضوء، أعرف طريقي،
stoop by the mint bed,
تنحني بسرير النعناع،
scoop a fistful of moist earth,
يغرف حفنة من الأرض الرطبة،
then grope for a chair,
ثم يتلمس طريقه بحثا عن كرسي،
spread a shawl, and sit,
ينشر منشفته ويجلس،
breathing in the wet green August air.
ينتفس في هواء أغسطس الأخضر الرطب.
This is the small, still hour
هذه ساعة صغيرة
before the newspaper lands in the vestibule like a grenade,
قبل القاء الصحيفة على المدخل مثل قنبلة،
the phone shrills, the computer screen blinks and glares awake.
صوت الهاتف يدوي، شاشة الحاسوب تومض وتتوهج.
There is this hour:
هناك هذه الساعة:
poem in my head, soil in my hand:
القصيدة في رأسي، التربة في يدي:
unnamable fullness.
امتلاء لا اسم له.
This hour, when blood of my blood
هذه الساعة، دم دمي
bone of bone, child grown to manhood now --
عظامي، طفل يصير رجلًا
stranger, intimate, not distant but apart --
غريب، حميم ليس بعيدًا ولكن بمعزل
lies safe, off dreaming melodies
يرقد بسلام، على أنغام حالمة
while love sleeps, safe, in his arms.
بينما ينام الحب بسلام على ذراعيه.
To have come to this place,
أتيت إلى هذا المكان،
lived to this moment:
عشت حتى هذه اللحظة:
immeasurable lightness.
ضوء لا يقاس.
The density of black starts to blur umber.
كثافة الأسود تطمس البني القرمزي.
Tentative, a cardinal's coloratura,
تجريبي،
then the mourning dove's elegy.
ثم مرثاة الحمامة الصباحية.
Sable glimmers toward grey;
بصيص قاتم تجاه الرمادي:
objects emerge, trailing shadows;
الأشياء تظهر وزائدة الظلال:
night ages toward day.
الصباح على وشك.
The city stirs.
تدب الحياة في أوصال المدينة.
There will be other dawns, nights, gaudy noons.
سنشهد صباحات آخرى، وليال وفترات ظهيرة ساطعة.
Likely, I'll lose my way.
سأفقد طريقي.
There will be stumbling, falling,
سيكون هناك عثرة وسقوط
cursing the dark.
ولعن الظلام.
Whatever comes,
أيّا كان ما سيأتي،
there was this hour when nothing mattered,
ستكون هذه الساعة حينما لا يهم شيء،
all was unbearably dear.
كله غير قابل للإحتمال يا عزيزي.
And when I'm done with daylights,
وعندمي أنتهي من ضوء النهار،
should those who loved me grieve too long a while,
سيتوجب على أولئك الذين أحبوني الحزن وقتًا طويلًا،
let them remember that I had this hour --
دعهم يتذكرون أني عشت هذه الساعة
this dark, perfect hour --
هذا الظلام هو أفضل ساعة
and smile.
وكذلك ابتسامة.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)